Guide to the Walter Freeman and James Watts collection, 1918-1988 MS0803.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Walter Freeman and James Watts collection
1918-1988
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Freeman, Walter
MS0803.UA
77.5 Linear Feet
Collection contains 77.5 linear feet of material accumulated by Dr. Walter Freeman and Dr. James W. Watts during the course of their medical careers, specifically their work on psychosurgery. The materials range in date from 1918-1988 (bulk 1940-1965) and consists of patient medical files, correspondence, articles and reprints, books, manuscripts, conference and research notes, photographs, oral histories, and medical equipment. Most of the records were produced as a direct result of their professional work at The George Washington University.
Restrictions on Access
Series 5, Patient records, are closed to research. Requests for access to patient records should be addressed to Special Collection staff.
Series 2 contain videos of patients; the full videos are also restricted. A shorter version is available for researchers.
The remainder of this collection is undergoing a review for confidential psychiatric patient records on an on-demand basis. Although a significant portion of the collection has already been reviewed, portions remain that must be reviewed by an archivist before access can be granted. Please allow additional time for this process when planning research in this collection. Confidential patient records identified in series 1 and 2 have been moved to restricted subseries, which are entirely closed to research. Requests for access should be addressed to Special Collection staff.
Acquisition Information
The Walter Freeman/James Watts collection, originally donated to the Himmelfarb Library of The George Washington University Medical School in 1980, was transferred to University Archives in April 2000.
Biographical Note
The Walter Freeman/James Watts collection, originally donated to the Himmelfarb Library of The George Washington University Medical School in 1980, was transferred to University Archives in April 2000. The collection represents the work of the first American team of doctors in psychosurgery. Dr. Walter Freeman (1895-1972) and his colleague Dr. James Winston Watts (1904-1994), developed a technique for neurosurgery on the frontal lobes of the brain commonly known as "lobotomy." Although considered a somewhat primitive practice by today's standards, this operation achieved a certain amount of success in significant numbers of patients suffering from severe depression, anxiety, and nervousness, and pain. (Success rate figures vary greatly.)\
This collection is of great value to scholars interested in the development of psychosurgery in the United States, since Freeman and Watts were pioneers in the field. (The first and second editions of their book Psychosurgery in the Treatment of Mental Disorders and Intractable Pain, published in 1942 and 1950, respectively, are contained in the collection.) Another collection in U niversity Archives related to this subject is the Thelma Hunt Papers, who was a Professor of Psychology at GW, and collaborated with Freeman and Watts on their book.
Walter Jackson Freeman II (1895-1972) earned world-wide fame for his work in the field of lobotomy. Freeman was born Philadelphia on Nov. 14, 1895 and received an A.B. from Yale in 1916, an M.D. from the University of Pennsylvania in 1920, and a Ph.D. from Georgetown University in 1931. He was professor of neurology at The George Washington University from 1926-1954, and became fascinated with psychosurgery (the scientific treatment of mental disorders by means of brain surgery). Freeman left GW in 1954 but continued his work in California, performing lobotomies and following-up on patients he had cared for up until his death on May 31 1972. He married Marjorie Lorne Franklin in 1924, and they had six children.
James Winston Watts (1904-1994) partnered with Freeman until 1949. He was born in Lynchburg, Virginia and graduated from the Virginia Military Institute and the University of Virginia Medical School in 1928 (where he was elected to Phi Beta Kappa and Alpha Omega Alpha honorary societies). He worked with John Fulton at Yale as a research fellow after medical school, and in 1935 joined the staff of the Department of Neurosurgery and Neurological Surgery at The George Washington University Hospital, where he remained until his retirement in 1969. He was married to Julia Harrison Watts and had two children. After his official retirement, Watts continued to work with the George Washington University Medical Center (including an oral history project) into the late 1980's and he died in 1994.
The study of psychosurgery has its origins in the last decades of the nineteenth century, when Gottlieb Burckhardt, a Swiss physician, performed operations in 1891 to remove parts of the cortex of six schizophrenic patients. After the surgery, some of the patients became calmer, although Burkhardt was criticized by medical authorities at the time for performing such a radical procedure. In the 1930's, Egas Moniz, a Portuguese neuropsychiatrist, built on the work Carlyse Jacobsen and John Fulton had done on primates. He proposed operating on a human subject, surgically cutting the nerve fibers connecting the frontal and prefrontal cortex to the thalamus, which is responsible for relaying sensory information to the cortex. In this way, Moniz reasoned, an interruption of the disruptive thoughts and behaviors of the psychotic patient might occur. Working with a colleague, he developed a surgical technique called leukotomy, in which holes were drilled in the head and a special wire knife, called a leukotome, was inserted into the brain matter. Moniz reported that in several cases severely agitated, anxious, or depressed patients showed improvement in their symptoms, although he cautioned using this technique as a last resort only. Walter Freeman read Moniz's reports, and embraced the idea of leukotomy. In September of 1936 Freeman and Watts operated on a 63 year-old woman who was suffering from depression, agitation, and fear. Following the operation, she was calm and her sense of terror seemed to have disappeared. After performing several more procedures, they published their first report in November, stating that anxiety, confusion, phobias, hallucinations, and delusions had been relieved or erased entirely in some patients. There was a down side to the procedure, which the doctors recognized, saying "Every patient probably loses something by this operation, some sparkle, some spontaneity, some flavor of their personality." Freeman and Watts changed the name of the procedure from "leukotomy" to "lobotomy," to distinguish their technique from that used by Moniz. They perfected what came to be known as the "Freeman-Watts Procedure," after much experimentation, but began to perceive the limitations of this operation early on. The initial professional reaction to the operations drew outraged responses from psychoanalysts and psychiatrists, although these reservations were not voiced to the public at the time. The introduction and wide acceptance around this time of shock therapies soon appeared a more acceptable alternative to lobotomies. Freeman was a neurologist, and neurologists had traditionally taken the view that there were physical causes for mental illness that required physical treatment. Psychiatrists on the other hand had argued that mental disorder was exclusively a problem of the mind. In the end, it was overcrowded institutions and limited mental health budgets that persuaded the medical community to adopt lobotomy as a popular course of treatment. The economic arguments were very strong: a lobotomy could be performed for $250 while it could cost $35,000 or more a year to maintain a patient in a hospital.
Walter Freeman was very good at convincing the press about the promises of lobotomy, and pushed it as a valid procedure. Up until 1945, Freeman had never actually performed a lobotomy himself, and wanted to develop a version of the operation that could be performed not just by neurosurgeons, but by anyone. During the winter of 1945, Freeman tried to develop a trans orbital (entry above the eye) approach to lobotomy, practicing on corpses. The instruments he and Watts were using were not strong enough to penetrate the orbital bone and kept breaking. Needing an implement that was slender, sharp, and strong, Freeman found precisely what he was looking for in a cheap, mass produced ice pick. Adapting it with a special hammer shaped head (which allowed easier manipulation), this instrument was used in the first trans orbital lobotomies in America in a procedure that came to be known as the "ice pick lobotomy." Armed with his new tool, Freeman was convinced that a trans orbital would be a simple piece of surgery not requiring the assistance of a neurosurgeon. He decided that he would operate on his first living patient without telling Watts, not dwelling on his own lack of surgical experience.
By his tenth patient, Freeman felt confident enough to inform Watts of what he had been doing. Watts was not happy, since he believed only a trained neurosurgeon should perform such an operation, and threatened to break with Freeman if he continued. It was the beginning of the end of their relationship and within months Watts left the joint practice they ran. By 1948, when Freeman was elected president of the American Board of Psychiatry and Neurology, the Freeman Watts standard lobotomy had been performed on as many as 20,000 individuals worldwide. In 1949, Egas Moniz won the Nobel Prize for Medicine for his pioneering work in psychosurgery, which in turn lent increased credibility to the practice of lobotomies. Between 1939 and 1951, some 18,000 lobotomies had been performed in the United States alone. By the early 1950's, rumblings about the effects of the lobotomy could be heard, as it was being used as a first, rather than a last resort by doctors. Post operative infections and fatalities were common, with autopsies showing large areas of the brain, not just selective nerves, being destroyed. It was impossible to judge recovery in many patients, and the inert, emotionless, inhuman, quality of those lobotomized began to revolt the public. Lobotomies were finally seen for what they were: not a cure, but a way of managing patients. It was seen by many doctors as just another form of restraint, and as some have put it, a mental straitjacket applied permanently over the brain.
For more information on Freeman/Watts and lobotomy, see the following websites:
http://www.geocities.com/~themistyone/freeman01.htm
http://www.psychosurgery.org/index.htm
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains 77.5 linear feet of material accumulated by Dr. Walter Freeman and Dr. James W. Watts during the course of their medical careers, specifically their work on psychosurgery. The materials range in date from 1918-1988 (bulk 1940-1965) and consists of patient medical files, correspondence, articles and reprints, books, manuscripts, conference and research notes, photographs, oral histories, and medical equipment. Most of the records were produced as a direct result of their professional work at The George Washington University.
The collection is presently arranged in five series; Walter Freeman Papers; James Watts Papers; Publications - General; George Washington University Hospital; and Patient Records (patient files, case reports). The collection as a whole presents a quite full examination of the subject of lobotomy. The collection, originally donated to the Himmelfarb Library of The George Washington University Medical School in 1980, was transferred to University Archives in April 2000. Staff at the Himmelfarb Library years ago "processed" the collection, but not to archival standards. For example, original letters have been scotch taped and stapled in an attempt to house them in artificial folders. Some have been left as they are for the sake of simplicity and so as not to damage the documents further in attempting to reverse the attachment.
Collection Organization
Organized into 5 series: Walter Freeman Papers; James Watts Papers; Publications - General; George Washington University Hospital; and Patient Records (patient files, case reports).
Portugal; Rome (Italy); Paris (France); Frontal lobotomy; Neurology; United States; Psychosurgery; Washington (D.C.); Photographs; Watts, James W. (James Winston); Moniz, Egas; George Washington University. School of Medicine and Health Sciences; Freeman, Walter; Hirose, Sadao; George Washington University
- Walter Freeman Papers, 1918-1972; MS0803 Series 1; 11.5 Linear feet (Box 19, Box 18, Box 17, Box 16, Box 15, Box 14, Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 8, Box 9, Box 10, Box 12, Box 11, Box 50, Box 13, Box 21, Box 22)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series comprises the papers of Dr. Walter Freeman. It consists of 11.5 linear feet of material, and ranges in date from 1918-72. It is divided into the following groups: correspondence; personal papers; manuscripts; publications; conferences papers, lectures; research; books; photographs; and artifacts.
  The correspondence material consists of 3 linear feet, including Christmas cards former patients exchanged with Dr. Freeman over the years. The materials are arranged chronologically by subject and range in date from 1923-72. Prominent in this sub-series is Freeman's correspondence with Egas Moniz, correspondence while living abroad in Paris and Rome after graduating from medical school, and correspondence with publisher Charles C. Thomas regarding the book Psychosurgery published in 1942.
  The personal papers material consists of 1 linear foot of Freeman's lecture notes while a medical student while at the University of Pennsylvania, and notes on essays on various subjects, as well as Freeman's C.V. and an FBI report on him (gift of Walter Freeman III in November 2003). The materials are arranged alphabetically and range in date from 1918-72.
  The manuscripts material consists of 1.5 linear foot of Freeman's writings (unless otherwise noted), including "Adventures in Lobotomy" (incomplete), a paper outlining the development of the department of neurology at GW, and his autobiography. This series also includes two theses about Freeman written by students at Harvard University. The materials are arrange alphabetically and range in date from ca.1920-88.
  The publications material consists of 2.5 linear feet of Freeman's publications, and includes ten bound volumes (which contain a list of articles), and others are listed individually. Many of the publications were co-authored with James Watts. They are arranged chronologically and range in date from 1921-71.
  The conferences papers, lectures material consists of 1 linear foot of materials related to conferences Freeman attended and papers he presented. The materials are arranged alphabetically and range in date from 1919-68.
  The research material consists of 0.5 linear feet of Freeman's research notes and reports. The materials are arranged alphabetically and range in date from 1921-61.
  The books material consists of 1 linear feet of books written by Freeman, and include Psychosurgery (1942 and 1950 editions, as well as the manuscript for 1942 edition) and Neuropathology: The Anatomical Foundation of Nervous Diseases (1933). It also contains news clippings and magazine articles on Freeman and lobotomy. The material ranges in date from 1923-80.
  The photographs material consists of 0.5 linear feet, and includes a photo of Freeman and Watts operating on a patient, Egas Moniz, the portrait of Freeman that hangs in Himmelfarb Library, and family photos. They are arranged alphabetically and range in date from 1916-71.
  The artifacts material consists of 0.5 linear feet of medical instruments belonging to Dr. Freeman, including leucotomes and an ice pick that Freeman may have used to perform transorbial lobotomies).
  - Correspondence, 1918-1972; MS0803 Subseries 1.1
    - Davidson Lecture Fund, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Hirose, Sadao, 1955-1972 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Letters of acknowledgement for reprints, 1957-1959 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Letters of acknowledgement for reprints, 1961-1967 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Moniz, Egas, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Moniz, Egas, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Moniz, Egas, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Moniz, Egas, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Moniz, Egas, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Moniz, Egas, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Moniz, Egas, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Moniz, Egas, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Moniz, Egas, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Moniz, Egas, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Moniz, Egas, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Moniz, Egas, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Moniz, Egas, 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Death of Egas Moniz, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - regarding book "Psychosurgery,", 1941-1942 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - regarding Dr. Luigi Perria, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - resignation from St. Elizabeth's Hospital, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - West Virginia Psychological Project, 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Personal Correspondence and sketches (Paris), 1923 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Personal Correspondence and sketches (Rome and Vienna), 1923-1924 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Personal Correspondence and sketches [1/3], 1924-1926 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Personal Correspondence and sketches [2/3], 1924-1926 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Personal Correspondence and sketches [3/3], 1924-1926 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Personal Letter to Yale roommate's father, 11/28/1918 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Personal Papers, 1918-1972; MS0803 Subseries 1.2
    - "The Ambulance by An Interne" by Walter Freeman, 1919 ca. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Application for Renewal of Narcotic Privileges, 1949-1952 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Bills and Insurance Policy, 1939-1948 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - "Collection of Themes", 1918 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence between Dr. Keen and Adm. Stitt regarding appointment of Freeman (grandson of Keen), 1924 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Curriculum Vitae and FBI Report on Freeman, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
      General note
      Donation from Walter Freeman III, November 2003
    - D.C. Unemployment and Social Security taxes, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - D.C. Unemployment and Social Security taxes, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - D.C. Unemployment and Social Security taxes, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - D.C. Unemployment and Social Security taxes, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Effect of Thawing on the CO2 Production of Sciatic Nerve of Frog., 1919 ca. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - "Five Elements - And Life", 1924 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Good Driving Contest, by Walter Freeman, 1915 ca. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - H. Douglas Singer and the American Board of Psychiatry and Neurology, by Walter Freeman, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Handbook of the American Board of Psychiatry and Neurology, Inc., 1939 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Lecture notes in General Pathology and Physiology, University of Pennsylvania (notes taken by Walter Freeman) [1/3], 1917-1918 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Lecture notes in General Pathology and Physiology, University of Pennsylvania (notes taken by Walter Freeman) [2/3], 1917-1918 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Lecture notes in General Pathology and Physiology, University of Pennsylvania (notes taken by Walter Freeman) [3/3], 1917-1918 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Obituary of Earl Baldwin McKinley, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Lectures and Clinics on Medicine and Surgery and Allied Subjects, University of Pennsylvania (notes taken by Walter Freeman), 1918-1920 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - On Beards, With Special Reference to My Own, 1935 ca. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Perspectives on the American Board of Psychiatry and Neurology, by Hugo Carmichael, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Preliminary Lecture by Dr. Monro on Surgery and Medicine, notes compiled by Walter Freeman, 1916 ca. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Psychological Plaques by Walter Freeman, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - "Maternity: Abstract of a letter of a student Intern to a friend", 1918 ca. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Obituary, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - The Religion of Science, 1920 ca. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Santa Clara-Monterey Psychiatric Society "Let George Do It", 03/09/1959 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Suppressed magazine article "Lobotomy-Commies Secret for World Domination,", 09/1956 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - To the Little Unseen (poem about the developing child), 1955 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Trip of the month to Europe in, 12/1956 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Walter Reed Army Hospital employment, 1951-1954 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Manuscripts, 1918-1972; MS0803 Subseries 1.3
    - Adventures in Lobotomy: Eqas Moniz, Chapter 1, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Adventures in Lobotomy: The Fourth Estate, Chapter 4, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Adventures in Lobotomy: Drive-ins and Jute Boxes, Chapter 5, undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Adventures in Lobotomy: Saw Dust Trail, Chapter 6, undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Adventures in Lobotomy: Prefrontal Lobotomy, Chapter 7, undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Air Castles [from Diseased Imaginations], 07/1958 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Chemical Flogging, 1920 ca. (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Democracy versus Autocracy in the Home (Children and Adult Behavior), 1930 ca. (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - The Development of Neurology at GWU, 1925-1954 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Drugs that Affect the Mind, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Freeman's Autobiography (redacted copy), 1970 ca. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Frontiers of Multiple Sclerosis, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Keeping Covered at Night, 1925 ca. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Machine Methods and Medicine, 1930 ca. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Mental Mechanisms and Psychosurgery, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - The Mind and the Body by Walter Freeman, 1936 ca. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - New Explorations of the Psyche, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Physiological Psychology (with James Watts), 1944 ca. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Psychiatric "Dynasties" in the United States, 1957 ca. (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Psychosurgery: 1936-1946, with James Watts (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Some Observations on Obsessive Ruminative Tendencies Following Interruption of the Frontal Association Pathways, with James Watts, 12/09/1937 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Thesis "A Disappointing Therapy: The Decline of Frontal Lobotomies in the Early 1950s" by Christopher Carter, Harvard University, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Thesis "The Theory and Practice of Psychosurgery: Dr. Walter Freeman and the Lobotomy Era" by Kenneth Rothfield, Harvard University, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - With Camera and Ice-Pick in Search of the Super Ego, 04/22/1960 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Publications, 1918-1972; MS0803 Series 1.4
    - Bound Publications, 1921-1930 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Bound Publications, 1928-1936 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Bound Publications, 1931-1935 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Bound Publications, 1936-1940 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Bound Publications, 1936-1954 (Box 12, Item 1)
    - Bibliography for articles on psychosurgery, 1929-1949 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - The Columnar Arrangement of the Primary Afferent Centers in the Brain-Stems of Man, 1927 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Mental Effects of Fatigue, 1928 ca. (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Lewis Morgan- Notebooks of a Tory Medical Student (with Freeman family genealogy chart), 1930 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Psychochemistry Some physicochemical Factors in Mental Disorders, 1931 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Torula Infections of the Central Nervous System, 1931 (Box 14, Folder 6)